<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><?xml-stylesheet href="http://www.blogger.com/styles/atom.css" type="text/css"?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:openSearch='http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearchrss/1.0/'><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593</id><updated>2007-01-06T20:05:38.711Z</updated><title type='text'>Wooden Spoon</title><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/blog.html'></link><link rel='next' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default'></link><link rel='http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/US/atom.xml'></link><author><name>louise</name></author><generator version='7.00' uri='http://www2.blogger.com'>Blogger</generator><openSearch:totalResults>82</openSearch:totalResults><openSearch:startIndex>1</openSearch:startIndex><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-8933879257087009160</id><published>2007-01-05T14:39:00.000Z</published><updated>2007-01-06T20:05:38.739Z</updated><title type='text'>Surprise cake</title><content type='html'>&lt;div style="float: right; margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;"&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/345177053/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/147/345177053_dd0f4d0cf8_m.jpg" alt="" style="border: 2px solid rgb(0, 0, 0);" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="margin-top: 0px;font-size:0;" &gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/345177053/"&gt;Surprise cake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.leitesculinaria.com/recipes/cookbook/surprise_cake.html"&gt;The picture&lt;/a&gt; looked quite appetising. You can see it too if you have a copy of 'Jamie's Kitchen' by Jamie Oliver. Go ahead, take a look. "That looks good" I thought. "That looks moist, a little crumbly, a lovely teatime cake". And I even had beetroot. the recipes most esoteric ingredient, lying around from my organic box a few weeks ago. So I set to work. Something should have tipped me off though. Maybe the use of olive oil instead of butter or another fat. Maybe the need for virtually a whole jar of honey to sweeten it, as there was no other sugar in the recipe. And maybe the colour of the batter after I had added the beetroot mash. It was purple - very purple indeed. But I persevered, popped it in the oven, and prepared to unveil it for pudding that evening when my parents were coming round to eat.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Everyone was suitably amused at the colour, and not a little apprehensive when they heard that this was a beetroot-based cake. But all bravely accepted and tasted a slice. I think it was my other half who first voiced his opinion. "This is terrible" he said. Unfortunately my mum and I were pretty much in agreement. There was no getting away from it - it tasted mostly of beetroot and little else. It wasn't sweet enough to really be cake, with a harsh, bitter note which I put down to the beetroot combined with  my use of Chestnut Honey. My Dad bravely finished his slice, but could not be prevailed on to accept seconds. And the conclusion? Beetroot and cake are not natural partners, so beware any recipe that calls for over 1lb of them.  And Jamie Oliver must have been thinking of an entirely different recipe when he took that photo.  Reassuringly, I have not been the only one to come to these conclusions  - &lt;a href="http://www.magma.ca/%7Eefung/blog/2005/08/surprise-cake.html"&gt;others have had a similar experience&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class="on" style="display: block;" id="formatbar_CreateLink" title="Link" onmouseover="ButtonHoverOn(this);" onmouseout="ButtonHoverOff(this);" onmouseup="" onmousedown="CheckFormatting(event);FormatbarButton('richeditorframe', this, 8);ButtonMouseDown(this);"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2007/01/surprise-cake'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/8933879257087009160'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/8933879257087009160'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-492605911872577821</id><published>2006-12-29T21:53:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-12-29T22:25:40.943Z</updated><title type='text'>January Cooking</title><content type='html'>In the reading time afforded by the Christmas holidays, I have been composing a list of recipes to tackle in the next few weeks. This started out at a mental list, but then I committed it to post-it, and now I'm posting it for the world to see - in the hope that it will help me actually tackle them all.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a style="font-weight: bold;" href="http://www.channel4.com/life/microsites/N/nigella/xmasbites2.shtml#recipe2"&gt;Lentil &amp; Chestnut Soup&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0701180331?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0701180331"&gt;Feast: Food That Celebrates Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=2&amp;a=0701180331" alt="" style="border: medium none  ! important; margin: 0px ! important;" border="0" height="1" width="1" /&gt; by Nigella Lawson&lt;br /&gt;I made this a couple of years ago, and spent ages trying to remember where I got the recipe from. All I remembered that it had chestnuts, and was the best, most wintry soup I made that year. This one I accomplished this afternoon - there's no picture, because it's not the most exciting soup to look at, as you might expect from the ingredients list.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a style="font-weight: bold;" href="http://www.channel4.com/life/microsites/N/nigella/xmasbites3.shtml"&gt;Rudolph Pie&lt;/a&gt; also from Feast&lt;br /&gt;This is to use up the cold venison I have in my fridge from Boxing Day at my parents house. Going to do this tomorrow.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Marmalade&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Blood Orange Marmalade I made last year is nearly out, so time to  make some more as soon as Seville Oranges are in the shops. This year I will either use the recipe from my new copy of the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1841882046?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=1841882046"&gt;The Cranks Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;amp;a=1841882046" alt="" style="border: medium none  ! important; margin: 0px ! important;" border="0" height="1" width="1" /&gt; or from MFK Fisher's description of her family recipe in &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0099422646?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=0099422646"&gt;With Bold Knife and Fork&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;amp;a=0099422646" alt="" style="border: medium none  ! important; margin: 0px ! important;" border="0" height="1" width="1" /&gt;. This one sounds like it could be wonderful, but includes no very specific quantities and requires 3 days!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pumpkin &amp; Mango Chutney Parcels&lt;br /&gt;Pasta stuffed with the butternut squash I've got sitting in the vegetable box.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Ginger Cake&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ginger cake always goes down well in our house - it lasts ages, and goes very well with tea. &lt;a href="http://lifeandhealth.guardian.co.uk/experts/danlepard/story/0,,1937937,00.html"&gt;Dan Lepard's recipe in the Guardian&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago looks like a good one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Chips&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Jeffrey Steingarten's article on the perfect French Fry in &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0747260974?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=0747260974"&gt;The Man Who Ate Everything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;amp;a=0747260974" alt="" style="border: medium none  ! important; margin: 0px ! important;" border="0" height="1" width="1" /&gt; includes a description of how to make chips at home following Joel Robuchon's home method. The idea is apparently to put the cold cut-up potatoes into cold oil and heat the whole thing up together, thereby giving them the first cooler cooking followed by the hotter second frying, all in one go.</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/12/january-cooking'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/492605911872577821'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/492605911872577821'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-116740948096003261</id><published>2006-12-29T16:24:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-12-29T16:50:46.382Z</updated><category scheme='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#' term='nokneadbread'></category><category scheme='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#' term='bread'></category><category scheme='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#' term='baking'></category><title type='text'>No-knead Bread</title><content type='html'>&lt;div style="float: right; margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;"&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/337419593/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/123/337419593_595ae05c7c_m.jpg" alt="" style="border: 2px solid rgb(0, 0, 0);" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="margin-top: 0px;font-size:0;" &gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/337419593/"&gt;No-knead_bread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Like the rest of the blog-o-sphere, I have been trying out &lt;a href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;amp;cd=3&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nytimes.com%2F2006%2F11%2F08%2Fdining%2F08mini.html%3Fex%3D1167109200%26en%3D336ea0b5c4c13ec3%26ei%3D5070&amp;amp;ei=C0KVRazoELTqwgHe_ZiVAg&amp;usg=__cLvhq3c-_am6vqLZFLTRhLESK9s=&amp;amp;sig2=83uEJqDwtdZQ9sjgTf_AfQ"&gt;Jim Lahey's No Knead Bread recipe&lt;/a&gt; over recent weeks. This was first published (with video!) by &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/pages/dining/index.html"&gt;Mark Bittman in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, and has since gone &lt;a href="http://www.realbakingwithrose.com/2006/12/no_knead_bread_nirvana_conclus.html#c015943"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.realbakingwithrose.com/2006/11/holy_bread.html"&gt;several &lt;/a&gt;times &lt;a href="http://www.amateurgourmet.com/the_amateur_gourmet/2006/11/make_bread.html"&gt;around&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.davidlebovitz.com/archives/2006/12/the_nail_in_the.html"&gt;the world&lt;/a&gt; via various blogs. I took the precaution of using &lt;a href="http://chocolateandzucchini.com/archives/2006/11/le_pain_quon_ne_petrit_pas.php"&gt;Clothilde's translation&lt;/a&gt; to grams, rather than those unreliable cups, having heard some reports of failures. This is my fourth go with it, and I have found it a very reliable recipe, consistently rising high and developing a very lovely crust. I have also combined it with some sourdough starter to get a slightly sour loaf. I am particularly enthusiastic about it as something that I can realistically tackle during the week, in just the time I have after work, between cooking dinner and eating dinner.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European No-Knead Bread&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;470g plain flour (I usually use half plain and half bread flour)&lt;br /&gt;350g water = 350ml&lt;br /&gt;10g salt - about 1.5 tsp&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp yeast&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mix the salt and yeast into the flour in a large bowl so they are evenly distributed. Pour in the water and mix with your fingers just until you get a single doughy mass that pulls away from the bowl. Then stop. Scrape your fingers off, and cover the bowl with cling film or a tea towel, and leave on your kitchen counter for 12-18 hours. I have left it for 20 hours in a cool kitchen and it was fine. You can make this last thing at night and return to it the next day after work.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Scrape the dough out of the bowl with a spatula, onto a floured worktop. Press the dough down with your fingertips and fold the left side over one third, then the right (like folding a letter). Flatten the dough a little again and fold top to bottom in the same way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sprinkle a teatowel with flour and some cornmeal/polenta or wheat bran if you have it. Place the down seam side down on the towel, and fold the edges over it. Leave for 2 hours to rise again. After an hour and a half, take a Pyrex or cast iron casserole dish with a lid, and put it into the cold oven. Heat it as hot as it will go - as close to 250C as you can.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After the 2 hours are up, take out the casserole, use the towel to tip in the dough (you don't have to be too delicate) and put the hot lid back on. Return to the oven for 30 minutes, then remove the lid and bake for 15 more minutes to brown the top and develop the crust further.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Then take it out and tip onto a wire rack. Allow it to cool before slicing - and eating with lots of butter!</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/12/no-kneadbread.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116740948096003261'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116740948096003261'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-116715645213172345</id><published>2006-12-26T18:06:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-12-26T18:07:32.223Z</updated><title type='text'>Christmas cookies</title><content type='html'>Food blogs have been awash with cookie recipes recently - those to eat, then &amp;#38; there, those to share with visitors and those to pack up and post off to deserving friends and relations. I have been busy with a variety of recipes this year - some new and some old. But rather than describe all in detail, here is a round-up of my Christmas baking:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oatmeal and Raisin Cookies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These come from a book purchased in America - appropriately enough, the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0395915376?ie=UTF8&amp;#38;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;#38;linkCode=as2&amp;#38;camp=1634&amp;#38;creative=6738&amp;#38;creativeASIN=0395915376"&gt;The All-American Cookie Book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;#38;l=as2&amp;#38;o=2&amp;#38;a=0395915376" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;, and have been a favourite for some time. They are apparently from a bed and breakfast known as Dairy Hollow House, and guests would be presented with one giant cookie in a little bag for their journey home. They are subtly spiced with ginger and cinnamon, and are crispy with just a little chewiness at the centre.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clementine Sables&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="http://orangette.blogspot.com/"&gt;Orangette&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="http://orangette.blogspot.com/2006/12/hop-to-it.html"&gt;Meyer lemon sables&lt;/a&gt;, and by the Buy One Get One Free offer on &lt;a href="http://www2.marksandspencer.com/foodmagazine/"&gt;Marks &amp;#38; Spencer&lt;/a&gt;'s clementines, I made these little chill-and-slice shortbread biscuits. My genius discovery is that sanding sugar, used for decorating cakes and cookies, especially in America, can be very cheaply and easily substituted by preserving sugar.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gingerbread Men&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;I have never made gingerbread men before, but the Christmassy-ness of them, plus the opportunity to play with icing faces and buttons proved too much to resist. I came across various ginger biscuit recipes at &lt;a href="http://chocolateandzucchini.com/archives/2006/11/biscuits_tres_gingembre.php"&gt;Chocolate and Zucchini&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.101cookbooks.com/archives/001536.html"&gt;101 Cookbooks&lt;/a&gt; and in several of my books, but in the end, I stuck to Nigella's Britishness in &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0701168889?ie=UTF8&amp;#38;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;#38;linkCode=as2&amp;#38;camp=1634&amp;#38;creative=6738&amp;#38;creativeASIN=0701168889"&gt;How to Be a Domestic Goddess: Baking and the Art of Comfort Cooking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;#38;l=as2&amp;#38;o=2&amp;#38;a=0701168889" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;. My only adjustments to her recipe were to reduce the black pepper, and to replace this by ground ginger. The biscuits were appropriately stiff and plain, but the spices developed beautifully over time, and now, a week since baking, they are very fragrant - although the icing did end up sticking them together in the cake tin.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chocolate Macaroons&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;I love chocolate &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macaron"&gt;macarons de paris&lt;/a&gt;, and have bought them from many places, including &lt;a href="http://www.miettecakes.com/"&gt;Miette&lt;/a&gt; bakery at the Ferry Plaza building in San Francisco, and from the &lt;a href="http://www.urbanpath.com/london/chinese/yauatcha.htm"&gt;Yauatcha&lt;/a&gt; concession at the &lt;a href="http://www.viewlondon.co.uk/taste-of-london-food-festival_index.html"&gt;Taste of London&lt;/a&gt; exhibition this year. However, since my first attempt at baking them myself at cooking school came out badly, I haven't really attempted them again. The main problems are 1) that characteristic smooth and shiny top and 2) the requisite chewiness combined with good chocolate flavour. There is no doubt that it is much easier to make them in the UK, where finely ground almonds are easily obtainable than to grind them yourself. This time I followed Flo Braker's quite precise instruction in her book Sweet Miniatures - some worked very well, others stayed crackly, but they all tasted pretty good :)&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/baking" rel="tag"&gt;baking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/christmas" rel="tag"&gt;christmas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cookies" rel="tag"&gt;cookies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/12/christmas-cookies.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116715645213172345'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116715645213172345'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-116306233862878753</id><published>2006-11-09T08:43:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-11-09T20:47:11.580Z</updated><title type='text'>Better cookies</title><content type='html'>&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/uploaded_images/cookies-763219.JPG"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0pt 10px 10px 0pt; float: left; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/uploaded_images/cookies-758381.JPG" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;There have been occasions for cookies recently - visits with friends, the need for something sweet on a cold night, so last week I determined that I would make some Oatmeal Raisin Cookies, which always seems to suit autumn well. My first thought was for a huge batch of Oatmeal Raisin cookies from my copy of The &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FAll-American-Cookie-Book-Nancy-Baggett%2Fdp%2F0395915376%2Fsr%3D8-1%2Fqid%3D1163104585%3Fie%3DUTF8%26s%3Dbooks&amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738"&gt;All-American Cookie Book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;l=ur2&amp;amp;o=2" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt; - they have gone down very well before, being tasty and crispy, with just the right amount of chew from the raisins. However, then I read &lt;a href="http://www.davidlebovitz.com/archives/2006/11/#000335"&gt;David Lebovitz's post&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/search?ie=UTF8&amp;keywords=Nick%20Malgieri&amp;tag=usingmainlysp-21&amp;index=books&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738"&gt;Nick Malgieri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=usingmainlysp-21&amp;amp;l=ur2&amp;amp;o=2" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;'s Chewy Oatmeal Raisin Cookies - low fat, but still good, made with some apple sauce instead of butter. As it happened, I had a couple of Bramley apples sitting in the fridge, so it seemed fated that I should try this recipe instead of my normal one. And I have to say it turned out very well - the cookies are chewy, but softer and moister than my usual ones, and without the usual shortening and butter combo, you can feel extra-virtuous about eating them!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I converted the recipe as posted by David into metric, and also added some spices that I usually add to the other recipe - and they worked very well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;140g plain flour&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp baking powder&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp bicarbonate of soda&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp ground ginger&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp ground cinnamon&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;br /&gt;30g butter, softened&lt;br /&gt;100g caster sugar&lt;br /&gt;90g light brown muscovado sugar&lt;br /&gt;1 large egg&lt;br /&gt;70g unsweetened apple sauce&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;br /&gt;135g rolled oats&lt;br /&gt;85g raisins&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preheat the oven to 190C (375F, 165C fan) and line a couple of baking sheets with baking parchment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mix the flour, baking powder, bicarb, spices and salt together so that the leavening is evenly distributed. Set aside.&lt;br /&gt;Cream the butter with the caster sugar (it will be much stiffer than usual) for 4 or 5 minutes. Mix in the brown sugar, followed by the beaten egg, apple sauce, and vanilla. I used my electric mixer for all this, but it's all perfectly possible with a  wooden spoon. Stir in the flour, oats and raisins until just combined - do not beat hard. Spoon tablespoons of the mixture (a bit smaller than a golfball) onto the baking sheets, and press with a fork to flatten a little. (I forgot this on the second sheet, but it didn't seem to make very much difference).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/uploaded_images/cookie_dough-717567.JPG"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/uploaded_images/cookie_dough-713752.JPG" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bake for 10-12 minutes, until they look dull on the surface, but are moist and soft, and are just golden at the edges.</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/11/better-cookies.html'></link><link rel='related' href='http://www.davidlebovitz.com/archives/2006/11/#000335'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116306233862878753'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116306233862878753'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-116063897057291100</id><published>2006-10-12T07:42:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-10-24T18:52:33.256Z</updated><title type='text'>Ale Cake</title><content type='html'>I recently made the same fruitcake for the 3rd time since hearing of the recipe early this year. I first heard the recipe on &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/"&gt;Woman's Hour&lt;/a&gt; in my lady-of-leisure days. It's a lovely recipe, simple and tasty, that has to be approached in quite a leisurely manner, requiring pre-soaking of the fruit and a long, long cooking time. However, it didn't occur to me that it was particularly unusual until the other weekend. The reason for making the cake this time around was to take as a birthday cake for a friend of ours that we were meeting up with in &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/177963905/"&gt;Woolacombe&lt;/a&gt; (that's a great surf spot in Devon by the way). As this cake (in fact, any fruitcake) can be made in advance and is robust enough to travel, it seemed an excellent choice. Both Friend and his fiancee loved the cake, but she made a particular point of saying that she usually dislikes fruit cake, but liked this one - which made me wonder, (as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrie_Bradshaw"&gt;Carrie Bradshaw&lt;/a&gt; might write):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes this one different?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/2006_06_fri_02.shtml"&gt;Ale Cake recipe&lt;/a&gt; fits with most other fruitcake recipes - it calls for you to cream together the butter and sugar, gradually beat in the eggs, fold in the flour gently, then the fruit, and back at a low temperature for a long time. The quirks are that the fruit is first soaked overnight in a generous quantity of beer, the sugar is dark brown muscovado, and the cake starts off at a moderate 160C for the first hour, lowering to 120C after that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So to think about it further, my starting point was to compare this recipe with a standard fruit cake - and what could be more standard than &lt;a href="http://www.deliaonline.com/recipes/the-classic-christmas-cake,1293,RC.html"&gt;Delia's Classic Christmas Cake&lt;/a&gt;? I also compared it with &lt;a href="http://www.deliaonline.com/recipes/traditional-dundee-cake,1218,RC.html"&gt;Delia's Dundee cake&lt;/a&gt; recipe. So here is the comparison of the quantities of the three recipes (I increased the quantities of the Dundee Cake recipe in proportion so that all used 4 eggs - the original uses 3 eggs):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;table border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;th align="left" width="25%"&gt;All in grams (unless stated)&lt;/th&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;th align="center" width="25%"&gt;Classic Christmas Cake&lt;/th&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;th align="center" width="25%"&gt;Ale Cake&lt;/th&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;th align="center" width="25%"&gt;Dundee Cake&lt;/th&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Fruit&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;900&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;875&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;600&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Liquid&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;45ml&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center" bgcolor="yellow"&gt;250ml&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Butter&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Sugar&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Eggs&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="left"&gt;Flour&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;td align="center" bgcolor="yellow"&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This ignores the minor ingredients, such as treacle &amp; spices, plus any chopped nuts, which shouldn't make any real difference to the texture. The two things that jump out at you are&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;the ale cake has much, much more liquid than the other two and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the dundee cake has a good deal more flour and less fruit in.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;I would expect this to mean a moister, and possibly flatter cake for the ale cake and a drier, 'cakier' texture for the dundee cake, which certainly fits Delia's description. The reason that the 250ml of beer in the ale cake doesn't play havoc with the cake batter is that the fruit is soaked overnight in it, and it is virtually all absorbed. So instead of a runny cake batter, what you have instead is lots of moist, plump fruit, that doesn't draw moisture from the cake after baking, and helps keep the cake moist and give it its almost fudgey texture. I suspect that the relatively mellow beer, compared to the brandy in the Christmas cake, helps to ensure that the flavour is not too sweet or too bitter, which some vine fruits can be.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So, as we are getting into Christmas Cake baking season, I am asking myself if this recipe would work well as a Christmas cake as well? I suspect that it could stand a few modifications to make it a bit more 'Christmassy', but would hold up well. Perhaps a shot of brandy in with the beer (would that be too weird?) and a bit more emphasis on citrus flavours - citrus juice and citrus zest and peel - would help give it that hot toddy feel. Or what about using red wine for soaking the fruit to give it a mulled wine feel? I will let you know how I get on with this one. Christmas cake is an important tradition in our household. Nathan's gran has baked him a personal Christmas cake for at least as long as I have known him. As she sadly died earlier this year, this will be our first Christmas without her, and there will be complaints if it is not up to her standard...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: right; font-size: 10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/fruitcake" rel="tag"&gt;fruitcake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/10/ale-cake.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116063897057291100'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116063897057291100'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-116063896658720805</id><published>2006-10-12T07:42:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-10-13T22:53:06.140Z</updated><title type='text'>Macaroni and other crunchy-topped things</title><content type='html'>I was going to write a recipe for Macaroni Cheese here, but it occurred to me that this wasn't very helpful. For one thing, it's a pretty simple recipe and most people have one somewhere. For another, I don't even have a recipe as such. This is one of those dishes that I have been cooking for as long as I can remember - an essential dish in my mother's repetoire, along with bolognese sauce (and by extension, lasagne) and quiche.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So instead of a recipe, I wanted to turn this into a set of guidelines for gratins, which is all that macaroni cheese is, at heart. Richard Ehrlich's compilation of &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/weekend/story/0,,880712,00.html"&gt;Guardian columns&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Perfect-Collected-Notes-Guardian-Weekend/dp/1904010830/sr=8-3/qid=1160774744/ref=sr_1_3/026-3717374-0816428?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books"&gt;'The Perfect ...'&lt;/a&gt; includes a wonderful 2 or 3 page set of instructions for the perfect potato gratin. I don't think I need to be so prescriptive, though. The definition of a good gratin can be much broader and more forgiving than this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sauce&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The sauce of a gratin, the part that allows all that bubbling goodness to take place, is composed of either a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechamel"&gt;bechamel sauce&lt;/a&gt;, or simply of milk or cream (and occasionally stock) combined with the starchy contents. Only raw potatoes are really starchy enough to thicken the sauce in the second case, so this method is restricted to gratin dauphinoise and its variations.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The best gratins are generally made with starchy contents (although fennel and chard gratins are both good). The homey, comforting nature of them - the need to serve them 'family style' from a communal dish - is enhanced with soft, starchy contents such as potatoes, pasta and root vegetables.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crispy top&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The original meaning of 'au gratin' was simply something browned under the grill, and this brown, crispy top remains the crucial element of this dish, and the reason for the wide, shallow gratin dish, giving a large area of crispy, with just the right amount of creamy underneath. The crispy top can either be achieved with cooking on the stove plus a stint under the grill, or by a long spell in the oven (which is the preferred method for gratin dauphinoise).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So, using these basic principles, we can create:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Macaroni Cheese - sauce is bechamel with cheese (aka cheese sauce), starch is &lt;em&gt;al dente&lt;/em&gt; cooked macaroni, and crispy top can be just cheese (for purists, and those who like lots of cheese - and who doesn't) or cheese and breadcrumbs.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gratin dauphinoise - lots of dispute about this one, but basically just milk and/or cream as the sauce, raw potato slices layered with onions and cooked in the oven until the top is brown.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Root vegetable gratin - slices of carrots, parsnips, swedes, cooked gently in a pan, combined with bechamel, then covered with breadcrumbs and baked.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And while away the whole autumn and winter with gooey, creamy, starchy dishes with crispy tops...Perfect.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/gratin" rel="tag"&gt;gratin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/macaroni" rel="tag"&gt;macaroni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/10/macaroni-and-other-crunchy-topped.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116063896658720805'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/116063896658720805'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-115809257182473403</id><published>2006-09-12T20:10:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-09-12T20:22:51.840Z</updated><title type='text'>Buffet food</title><content type='html'>This is a special post in response to Sam's &lt;a href="http://becksposhnosh.blogspot.com/2006/09/please-help-my-lovely-lovely-mum.html"&gt;heartfelt plea &lt;/a&gt;over at &lt;a href="http://becksposhnosh.blogspot.com/"&gt;Becks &amp; Posh&lt;/a&gt;. She wants recipe suggestions for her Mum to make for her own retirement party. As it happens, waaaaay back in February, I made a brunch buffet for a load of people, and the stand-out winner was the frittata. I wanted to make eggs (because you can't really call it brunch unless I have eggs) but I also wanted as much of the buffet as possible to be done in advance. So I made a baked frittata, assembled from various sources (including an Australian Women's Weekly book, and epicurious.com, if I remember rightly). It's a very forgiving recipe that lends itself to including leftovers, and can be cut into as small pieces as you need.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Breakfast Frittata&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;To fill one 30cm x 21cm (roughly 8" x 12") tin, cut into 12 large triangles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;6-8 charlotte potatoes, boiled until tender &amp; cooled&lt;br /&gt;3 onions, halved and roasted in the over for around 1 hr until caramelised&lt;br /&gt;1.5 - 2 cups frozen peas&lt;br /&gt;120g crumbled lancashire cheese&lt;br /&gt;8 eggs&lt;br /&gt;284ml carton double cream&lt;br /&gt;lots of salt &amp;amp; pepper&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chop the potatoes and onions into roughly pea-sized pieces. Crumble in the cheese. Beat the eggs in a separate bowl and pour over the vegetables with the cream. Mix around and pour into the foil-lined tin.&lt;br /&gt;Bake at 140C for around 40 minutes, or until just set in the middle. (Keeping the temperature low helps keep the texture creamy).&lt;br /&gt;Leave to cool, then store in the fridge. Unmould and cut into pieces while cold, then leave for an hour or so to come to room temperature before serving.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/09/buffet-food.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115809257182473403'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115809257182473403'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-115809141166216127</id><published>2006-09-12T19:55:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-09-12T20:03:31.690Z</updated><title type='text'>New house</title><content type='html'>We have just moved house to a new place in Chiswick near the river, and I'm really looking forward to exploring all the new foodie attractions down here, including:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fishworks.co.uk/restaurantchiswick.asp"&gt;FishWorks&lt;/a&gt; - near Turnham Green tube&lt;br /&gt;This chain of fish restaurants with fresh fish counters is very popular, but I've yet to make use of one. Fish is a real cooking blind spot for me - I'm so seldom inspired to do something more interesting than fry or bake it - so I'm going to try and branch out a bit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.oldshipw6.co.uk/"&gt;The Old Ship&lt;/a&gt; - on the river&lt;br /&gt;A nice pub that was hired for work's summer drinks a few weeks ago. Great river views, and they do decent food too.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://fodm.homestead.com/farmersmarket.html"&gt;Duke's Meadows' Farmers' Market&lt;/a&gt; (do you think I got all the apostrophes right there?!)&lt;br /&gt;Duke's Meadows is a great piece of common land, with playing fields, allotments and gardens. There is a small farmers market on Sundays - I went last weekend, but right at the end, and much of the produce was gone. Will try and get up earlier next time :)</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/09/new-house.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115809141166216127'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115809141166216127'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-115330201724451776</id><published>2006-07-19T09:23:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-07-27T21:09:49.433Z</updated><title type='text'>Midsummer House on a summer evening</title><content type='html'>For my birthday last week, my rather lovely husband booked us a meal at &lt;a href="http://www.midsummerhouse.co.uk/html/home.htm"&gt;Midsummer House&lt;/a&gt; in Cambridge, with a mutual friend of ours who was visiting from the States. Despite a 3 year stint in &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/search/?s=int&amp;amp;w=all&amp;amp;q=cambridge%2C+river&amp;amp;m=tags"&gt;the town on the banks of the Cam&lt;/a&gt;, I had never been there, but I had heard good things, so I was excited to see what it was like. It should also be noted that there is a considerable dearth of restaurants above the cheap student level in Cambridge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We arrived a touch late for our table, but the staff displayed not a hint of irritation. The dining space is a small conservatory area and one room in the house, but the tables are well spaced out, the restaurant focusing on quality in small quantities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There was a tasting menu, but we ordered from the a la carte menu, which was equally interesting. I ordered a fennel gazpacho, on the recommendation of the waiter, followed by turbot. Before our starters, we were treated to 2 amuses bouche (or amuses bouches??). The first was a pink grapefruit and champagne foam, presented from a siphon - like a soda siphon, but round - at the table. It was sharp, dry, and very refreshing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The second amuse reminded me a lot of a dish that we had at &lt;a href="http://www.mgmgrand.com/dining/atelier-joel-robuchon-french-restaurant.aspx"&gt;L'Atelier de Joel Robuchon&lt;/a&gt; in Las Vegas last year (oh, the jet set lifestyle!). It was a little glass jar, with a green pea foam, in which were lurking little tiger prawns, cubes of seaweed jelly, and peas. The foam was good and savoury, and really brought out the sweetness of the prawns.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The fennel gazpacho was poured into an elabourate plate of bits and pieces, including some sort of caramel used to make a little tube, which was filled with a yoghurt mousse and topped with little chips of freeze dried yoghurt. There was also delicate pieces of fennel and cucumber in there, and a quennelle of yoghurt sorbet. The flavours went beautifully together - all cool and delicate. And a chilled soup was the perfect thing for a hot, sticky evening.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The mains then came. My turbot came with a peanut and pistachio crust, a smear of squash puree, crisply wrapped asparagus, little broad beans, and a squirt of essence of vanilla added at the table. At first I thought the peanut and pistachio overpowered the fish, but taken with the sweet puree and vanilla essence, it helped to balance out the sweetness with the salty peanuts, and the fish was strong enough to stand up to it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Although we were pretty well filled at this point, we weren't strong enough to resist the dessert menu - especially when the chocolate fondant came with a particular recommendation. I ordered this, but before it came, we had another amuse. This was a strawberry with a little diced strawberry and cubes of strawberry jelly (they were very keen on little cubes of jelly). It looked like a standard cheesecake in a little mould, but at the table the moulds were removed to reveal a barely-held together cheesecake foam, on  top of biscuit crumbs. It was like a cross between a cheesecake and a cloud - one of the better uses of a foam I have come across.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After a suitable pause to digest (which I was very grateful for) the chocolate plate arrived. As well as a really good, properly liquid-centred chocolate fondant, there was also a scoop of  walnut ice-cream, a dark chocolate sauce with cubes of amaretto jelly and a long chocolate wafer with cacao nibs in it. It was a stunning plate of food, but the fondant was so rich that I barely tackled half of it. A smaller fondant would have allowed a better balance, but then it would probably be too difficult to get the baked outside with the liquid centre.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;All in all, it was an excellent meal, only enhanced by the opportunity to catch up with a friend.&lt;br /&gt;And as a postscript, I would like to wish Clotilde of &lt;a href="http://chocolateandzucchini.com/"&gt;Chocolate &amp;#38; Zucchini&lt;/a&gt; a Joyeux Anniversaire! as it's her birthday today.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cambridge" rel="tag"&gt;cambridge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/food" rel="tag"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/restaurant" rel="tag"&gt;restaurant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/07/midsummer-house-on-summer-evening.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115330201724451776'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115330201724451776'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-115115851075911298</id><published>2006-06-24T14:11:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-06-24T15:24:57.653Z</updated><title type='text'>Broad bean crostini</title><content type='html'>&lt;div style="float: right; margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;"&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/173796374/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img src="http://static.flickr.com/56/173796374_308d472f3a_m.jpg" alt="" style="border: solid 2px #000000;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 0.9em; margin-top: 0px;"&gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/173796374/"&gt;Broad bean crostini&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;  Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lunchtime rolls around and I have the following at my disposal:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Half a frozen foccacia&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;the end of a piece of St Chevrier Ash - a creamy, tangy goat's cheese&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;2 bags of broad beans (fava beans) from Hammersmith farmer's market on Thursday&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seems like a no-brainer, so I put the foccacia into the oven to defrost for 5 or 10 mintes. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Half an hour later, I have half a foccacia crispbread (you can see it in the background of the photo).&lt;p&gt;Well, at least it's not burnt, and sliced thinly the centre is still chewy and the edges crisp. I pod and blanch the broad beans and pop them out of their little grey skins. Half go into the fridge for tea, and half get 'bashed' in my mortar, Jamie Oliver-style, with salt, lemon juice, olive oil and a little grating of parmesan. I spread the St Chevrier on the thin foccacia slices, and top with the broad bean mush. It all turned out much better than those inauspicious beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/06/broad-bean-crostini.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115115851075911298'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/115115851075911298'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114796364494262089</id><published>2006-05-18T14:44:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-05-18T14:47:25.040Z</updated><title type='text'>Sport Relief</title><content type='html'>If you're in the UK, you can't have missed the Sport Relief publicity in the last few weeks. Being somewhat off the wagon, fitness-wise, we nevertheless decided that we could probably manage to run/walk/wheeze for a mile, so have signed up for the the &lt;a href="http://www.sportrelief.com/local-events/"&gt;Sport Relief Mile&lt;/a&gt; on July 15th.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sport Relief is part of the long-running charity &lt;a href="http://www.comicrelief.com/"&gt;Comic Relief&lt;/a&gt; and aims to help people in the poorest countries in the world as well as vulnerable people in the UK.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For this gargantuan effort of making it to the end of a 1609 metre course, we are asking for sponsorship. Please visit &lt;a href="https://secure.artezglobal.com/registrant/StartUp.aspx?SID=21477"&gt;my sponsorship page&lt;/a&gt; to donate. Alternatively, you could provide helpful suggestions for costumes or other themes in the comments - no promises though!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/sport relief" rel="tag"&gt;sport relief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/05/sport-relief.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114796364494262089'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114796364494262089'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114772492187376534</id><published>2006-05-15T20:26:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-05-16T12:40:39.916Z</updated><title type='text'>Turkish Delights</title><content type='html'>&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/146796525/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img alt="bazaar" src="http://static.flickr.com/45/146796525_c3d606660c_m.jpg" style="border: solid 2px #000000;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/146796525/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/146796525/"&gt;Stall at Spice Bazaar&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;I have just come back from a long weekend in Istanbul. Everyone told me before we went that it was an incredible city, and I wasn't disappointed. We heard the muezzins calling people to prayer at lunchtime while overlooking the Suleyman Mosque. We cruised along the Bosphorus and had a special performance from one of Turkey's foremost belly dancers (apparently - I mean, how would we know?!). We watched the red moon rise over the city from a restaurant in the hills. We saw the inside of the Haghia Sophia, a sight so awe-inspiring that it caused both a Roman Emperor (Justinian) and an Ottoman Sultan to prostrate themselves and thank their respective Gods the first time they saw it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I also (inevitably) visited the Spice Bazaar in the Old Town, where Istanbullus still come to buy their supplies for the week. I looked around at the spice stalls, shops selling fresh feta and other cheeses, stalls with Turkish Delight, ropes made of dates, baklava and all types of nuts and dried fruit. I settled for buying some spices and pomegranate molasses from a kind looking man in one of the hidden-away spice stalls. He was quite bemused that I would want the molasses - not something he sees many Europeans buying, I suspect. I also bought some Turkish coffee from Mehmet Effendi's stall - freshly roast and ground that morning. It smelled too good not to.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sumac&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is a dark red berry that is coarsely ground and used in Turkish cooking. It has a sour, lemony taste and is often sprinkled on meat (such as kebabs) or fish just before serving.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pomegranate Molasses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is a dark, syrupy liquid made by boiling down the juice from the sour pomegranate (rather than the sweet pomegranate whcih is usually used for juice). It is sour, as you might expect, but also has a slight sweetness which makes for a very interesting flavour.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I used my brand-new pomegranate molasses to make one of Claudia Roden's recipes (which also appears in her new book, Arabesque), Muhammara, a walnut and pomegranate paste.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/147530088/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img alt="muhammara" src="http://static.flickr.com/45/147530088_c3d606660c_m.jpg" style="border: solid 2px #000000;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/147530088/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/147530088/"&gt;Muhammara&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Muhammara&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;100g walnut pieces&lt;br /&gt;2 small slices of white bread, stale&lt;br /&gt;1 tbsp pomegranate molasses&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp ground cumin&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp chilli flake&lt;br /&gt;3 tbsp olive oil&lt;br /&gt;4 tbsp water&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Soak the bread briefly in water and then squeeze it out. Grind the walnuts in the food processor, then add the rest of the ingredients and puree, adding a little more water if it's too stiff.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This was much tastier than I had anticipated - bitter from the walnuts and pomegranate but with a little sweetness from the molasses. Next time I would add a little more chilli (Claudia also suggests stirring in some harissa), and maybe toasting the walnuts and cumin to bring out their flavours more.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/food" rel="tag"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/Istanbul" rel="tag"&gt;Istanbul&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/turkish" rel="tag"&gt;turkish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/05/turkish-delights.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114772492187376534'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114772492187376534'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114776892178549748</id><published>2006-05-15T21:54:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-05-16T08:42:56.926Z</updated><title type='text'>Ask Nigel (the science bit)</title><content type='html'>One of the pleasures of the Sunday papers for me us &lt;a href="http://lifeandhealth.guardian.co.uk/experts/nigelslater/"&gt;Nigel Slater's column&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/"&gt;Observer&lt;/a&gt;. The Internet allows me to create my own personal 'best of' Sunday paper, and not to have to get out of bed to read it (provided my laptop is in reach).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One of the things that they have added in the past year is a questions and answers section, where Nigel kindly answers reader's queries. While I find his answers interesting, they are not sufficiently scientific for my liking, so I thought I would have a go and providing some alternative answers to the same questions. &lt;a href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,,1773835,00.html"&gt;Here are Nigel's original answers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q Nigel, for flavour and nutrition, is it better to crush or chop cloves of garlic? Many thanks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;For flavour, the more you disrupt the garlic cells, the more of their flavour you release. So for a subtle flavour, slice it thinly, for more oomph, chop finely (my personal choice) and for maximum flavour, or where you need something smooth (e.g. to add to mayonnaise for aioli) crush it with salt using the side of a knife. For nutritional purposes, unless you're using bulbs and bulbs, whatever you do with the garlic is unlikely to affect the nutrition of the dish one way or another.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Q Is there a way to stop yogurt curdling and turning grainy when added to curry?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Yoghurt will curdle because the milk proteins denature - yoghurt is high in protein, and when heated too much, the protein molecules tangle with each other and form lumpy curds. This doesn't happen with cream, because there is too much fat in the way, so using a full-fat or greek yoghurt will help. You can also stabilise the yoghurt by adding something else to interfere with coagulation - starch. Mixing a little yoghurt with some cornflour (say 1 tsp for a 4 person curry) will thicken the yoghurt slightly and provide stability. Finally, make sure you add the yoghurt at the end. Cook the curry all the way, turn off the heat and just stir through the yoghurt. It's getting the yoghurt too hot that causes the curdling in the first place.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/food" rel="tag"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/yoghurt" rel="tag"&gt;yoghurt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/science" rel="tag"&gt;science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/05/ask-nigel-science-bit.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114776892178549748'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114776892178549748'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114727690639503483</id><published>2006-05-10T15:59:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-05-10T16:01:46.476Z</updated><title type='text'>Holidays</title><content type='html'>Have been on holiday recently (although that is obviously not sufficient excuse for the absence from this blog :). I'm off again to Turkey tomorrow, but expect more when I get back. Brief summary of the holiday:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Geneva - staying with friends&lt;br /&gt;Highlight - a long, *long* walk with beautiful views of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;q=geneva&amp;amp;ll=46.271512,6.228561&amp;amp;spn=0.220232,0.466232&amp;amp;t=k&amp;amp;om=1"&gt;Lake Geneva&lt;/a&gt;, seeing &lt;a href="http://www.ultimateungulate.com/Artiodactyla/Rupicapra_rupicapra.html"&gt;Chamois&lt;/a&gt; goats on the mountain and wildflowers everywhere.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/cornwall/webcams/webcam_bude.shtml"&gt;Bude, Cornwall&lt;/a&gt; - self-catering&lt;br /&gt;Highlights: a bit of bodyboarding, excellent fish and chips and clotted cream, and I finally finished '&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0826452094/qid=1147276329/sr=8-2/ref=sr_8_xs_ap_i2_xgl/202-0615788-1901428"&gt;Seven Basic Plots&lt;/a&gt;'.</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/05/holidays.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114727690639503483'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114727690639503483'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114297371123195480</id><published>2006-03-21T20:40:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-03-21T20:41:51.276Z</updated><title type='text'>British food</title><content type='html'>Reading my food blogs RSS feed, I came across a pair of Brit-related posts today. &lt;a href="http://www.justhungry.com/2006/03/masterchef_wrap.html"&gt;The first&lt;/a&gt; is from &lt;a href="http://www.justhungry.com/"&gt;i was just really very hungry&lt;/a&gt;, praising the most recent series of &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/food/tv_and_radio/masterchef/"&gt;Masterchef&lt;/a&gt; (Masterchef Goes Large! to give it's full title). I have to agree with maki that this has been a well-crafted reality show, much better than other shows with a similar format (although I haven't seen &lt;a href="http://www.bravotv.com/Top_Chef/"&gt;Top Chef&lt;/a&gt;, which she mentions).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The other post was from &lt;a href="http://www.accidentalhedonist.com/"&gt;Accidental Hedonist&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.accidentalhedonist.com/index.php/2006/03/21/the_names_of_british_foods"&gt;on the bizarre names given to British food&lt;/a&gt;. I won't completely rehash her post, but basically she describes a theory from a book called &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0563522720/qid=1142965595/sr=8-1/ref=sr_8_xs_ap_i1_xgl/203-6443630-1753519"&gt;Gastronaut&lt;/a&gt;, that British food tends to be looked down on by other cultures, not because of it's quality but because of the strange names of the dishes. My understanding is that what is considered traditional British food dates from somewhere between the 17th and 19th Centuries and so the names are as antiquated as that suggests. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Looking at her list, I only recognised 11 of the 25 there, but I thought I would run through my understanding of those 11. I have given my descriptions, and then went back through and added some more helpful links, so that you can get a better idea, and in some cases, the recipes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/food/recipes/mostof_blackpudding.shtml"&gt;Black Pudding&lt;/a&gt; - a blood sausage, very traditional and often served with a full fried breakfast&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/christmas2005/story/0,,1672804,00.html"&gt;Bubble and Squeak&lt;/a&gt; - a great leftovers dish, cabbage and potatoes fried together&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.foodinscotland.co.uk/recipes.html#clapshot"&gt;Clapshot&lt;/a&gt; - a root vegetable mash - like Neeps and Tatties, a Scottish dish&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.suppertonight.co.uk/cullenskink.htm"&gt;Cullen Skink&lt;/a&gt; - a traditional Scottish smoked haddock soup&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.post-gazette.com/food/20030313flummeryr9p9.asp"&gt;Flummery&lt;/a&gt; - a soft fruit pudding, like a fool&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nicecupofteaandasitdown.com/biscuits/previous.php3?item=12"&gt;Hob Nobs&lt;/a&gt; - oatmeal biscuits (cookies) made by McVities - not traditional at all, as far as I know!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/food/story/0,,1716660,00.html"&gt;Knickerbocker Glory&lt;/a&gt; - an elaborate banana and ice-cream dessert, usually served with a cherry on top&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.marmite.com/"&gt;Marmite&lt;/a&gt; - a salty spread, officially yeast extract - you either love it or you hate it (the website is great)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.foodtimeline.org/foodpuddings.html#spotted"&gt;Spotted Dick&lt;/a&gt; - a suet pudding, studded with raisins. Something of a standing joke, so almost never seen any more&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toad_in_the_hole"&gt;Toad-in-the-hole&lt;/a&gt; - sausages cooked in a Yorkshire pudding batter - still very popular, despite the name, as it's such a great combination.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;and that's without &lt;a href="http://www.foodinscotland.co.uk/recipes.html#clootie"&gt;Clootie dumplings&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe there is something to this theory...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/food" rel="tag"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/british" rel="tag"&gt;british&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/03/british-food.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114297371123195480'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114297371123195480'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114157283730873508</id><published>2006-03-05T15:33:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-03-05T15:33:57.640Z</updated><title type='text'>Nigel Slater</title><content type='html'>How nice to see our own Nigel Slater &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/05/magazine/305food.1.html?_r=1&amp;amp;oref=slogin&amp;amp;pagewanted=all"&gt;getting some press&lt;/a&gt; the other side of the water. They already know all about Nigella and Jamie from their respective TV series, but as Nigel is not one for the TV cameras, he hasn't really made an impression there yet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Incidentally, this New York Times article was penned by Julie Powell, author of &lt;a href="http://blogs.salon.com/0001399/"&gt;Julie &amp;#38; Julia&lt;/a&gt;, and blog and now &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0670915254/qid=1141572659/sr=8-1/ref=pd_ka_1/202-5299623-4779854"&gt;a book&lt;/a&gt; about cooking everything from Julia Child's book in one year.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And you can find a neat archive of Nigel Slater's writing for the Observer here:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://lifeandhealth.guardian.co.uk/experts/nigelslater/"&gt;http://lifeandhealth.guardian.co.uk/experts/nigelslater/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/newspaper" rel="tag"&gt;newspaper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/NigelSlater" rel="tag"&gt;NigelSlater&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/reviews" rel="tag"&gt;reviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/03/nigel-slater.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114157283730873508'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114157283730873508'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114140522408235377</id><published>2006-03-03T17:00:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-03-03T17:08:42.006Z</updated><title type='text'>Blood Orange Marmalade</title><content type='html'>&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/107243823/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://static.flickr.com/47/107243823_ff649325f8_m.jpg" align="right" style="border: solid 1px #000000;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/107243823/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/louise_marston/107243823/"&gt;marmalade.JPG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/louise_marston/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;I have something of a glut of citrus fruit at the moment, courtesy of my weekly organic box from &lt;a href="http://www.abel-cole.co.uk/"&gt;Abel and Cole&lt;/a&gt;, so my thoughts turned to marmalade. Although traditionally made with the sour Seville orange, it is also possible to use sweet oranges, especially if you up the acid and pectin content by adding lemons to the mix.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Marmalade is nothing more than orange jam, but the traditional recipe, originating in Dundee, requires two particular things - the afore-mentioned Seville orange, and finely or thickly sliced orange zest. The word marmalade comes from the portguese &lt;em&gt;marmelada&lt;/em&gt;, which originally described a quince jam something like quince cheese or &lt;em&gt;membrillo&lt;/em&gt;. Like quinces, citrus fruits are rich in pectin, the substance that sets jams and jellies into that particular firm and quivering consistency.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Basic marmalade principles are the same as those for other jams:&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8226; Extract the maximum pectin. This is usually done by gathering the pips from the fruit, sometimes also the pulp and pith, in a muslin bag and boiling it with the juice before removing it and squeezing the bag to extract the soluble pectin.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8226; Ensure there is plenty of acid. This helps to extract the maximum pectin and gives a better set. Extra lemon juice is often used for this, but it's not a particular problem for marmalade.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8226; Dissolve sugar completely before bringing the fruit and sugar mixture to a boil. This helps to prevent crystallisation&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The aim is to extract pectin, and then to make a 60-65% sugar solution with the fruit by boiling off the water until this setting point is reached. I based this recipe on one for &lt;a href="http://www.waitrose.com/food_drink/recipes/recipesearch/recipe/0301092-r01.asp"&gt;Sweet Orange Marmalade&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.waitrose.com/food_drink/wfi/index.asp"&gt;Waitrose Food Illustrated&lt;/a&gt; magazine, adding a step to increase the pectin, as suggested in other recipes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 lemons&lt;br /&gt;2 small pink grapefruit&lt;br /&gt;9 blood oranges&lt;br /&gt;500g granulated sugar&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zest the lemons, one grapefruit and 3 of the oranges using a vegetable peeler to remove just the zest. Finely julienne the zest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Juice all the fruit. There should be just over 1 litre.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Add the pips, pith and remaining flesh from the fruit into a square of muslin. Add this to a pan of water and boil for 45 minutes. Leave to soak overnight.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The next morning, squeeze all the pectin from the muslin and add with the water to the juice, zest and sugar in a large pan. Heat gently to dissolve the sugar, then bring to a simmer and boil for 1.5 hours, or until temperature reaches 104 degrees C. Start testing the set on a cold saucer, looking for a wrinkle on the surface when it is pushed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Let cool for 15 minutes or so before putting into sterilised jars (this helps make sure all the zest doesn't float to the top).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This looks beautiful, and is quite tart because of the grapefruit. It's possible that it would have benefited from the zest being blanched before adding to the marmalade to remove some of the bitterness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/cooking" rel="tag"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/food" rel="tag"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/marmalade" rel="tag"&gt;marmalade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/03/blood-orange-marmalade.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114140522408235377'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114140522408235377'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114107597917115582</id><published>2006-02-27T21:31:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-02-27T22:29:32.446Z</updated><title type='text'>Britain's Biggest Ever Robbery</title><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed tonight that at &amp;#163;53 116 760, &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/crime/article/0,,1719192,00.html"&gt;last week's Kent robbery&lt;/a&gt; was the biggest ever in the UK. This made me wonder how we rank in the world league table of robberies. What was the biggest ever robbery in the U.S.? What about Ireland? Were these others similar schemes, or more complicated? This sort of thing is a staple of Hollywood (and British) films, but how many of them sound like film plots?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Bank_of_Iraq"&gt;Iraq Central Bank&lt;/a&gt;, March 2003&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iraq Central Bank - theft of $900 million in U.S. bills and 82 million euros during the U.S.-led invasion. This seems to be considered the largest bank heist in history, and took place over several days. Although reports are a little hazy, this appears to have been Saddam Hussein's family claiming money from their "personal piggy-bank". Some reports indicate that Saddam's son Qusay directed the robbery, which involved little more than men arriving with a note from Saddam and then loading the cash into vans. Much of the money was later recovered from Saddam's palaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knightsbridge_Security_Deposit_robbery"&gt;Knightsbridge Safe Deposit Centre&lt;/a&gt;, London, 1987&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two men asked to hire a Safe Deposit box, and once inside the vault, they produced guns and overpowered the manager and other guards. They then displayed a sign telling the public that the vault was closed before letting in other accomplices. They broke open safe deposit boxes and left with an estimated &amp;#163;40 million. Several people were arrested after fingerprints were found on one of the deposit box doors and matched to an Italian who was also wanted in connection with other armed robberies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banco_Central_robbery_at_Fortaleza"&gt;Banco Central, Forzaleza&lt;/a&gt;, Brazil, August 2005&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The robbery of 164 million reals (&amp;#163;38.6 million) from a Central Bank vault. The robbers spent 3 months digging a 260 feet tunnel from a house they had rented near the bank. One weekend, they burst from the tunnel into the vault and took the cash away. The aftermath of this incident is continuing - several people have been arrested and various people suspected of the robbery or related to the suspects have since been abducted or killed, presumably by people who know that have enough money to pay large ransoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Bank_robbery"&gt;The Northern Bank Robbery&lt;/a&gt;, December 2004&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Famously Ireland's biggest ever robbery was the theft of &amp;#163;26.5 million from the Northern Bank in Belfast in which the IRA were implicated. This robbery, like the Tonbridge incident, involved the families of bank employees being held hostage in order that the robbers could be given access to the vault.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's striking how many of these stories resemble film plots - I'm sure that a film of the Brazilian robbery is in the works as we speak. But few of these have Hollywood happy endings - arrest, kidnap, death. It's not an easy life for a bank robber, it would seem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/bank" rel="tag"&gt;bank&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/robbery" rel="tag"&gt;robbery&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/uk" rel="tag"&gt;uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/02/britains-biggest-ever-robbery.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114107597917115582'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114107597917115582'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114070357751566774</id><published>2006-02-23T14:00:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-02-27T21:56:23.023Z</updated><title type='text'>Film trailers</title><content type='html'>I've spent some time today (probably more than warranted) looking at some new film trailers, and I thought I would give a little digest of the best:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/trailers/sony_pictures/marieantoinette/"&gt;Marie Antoinette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the next film from Sofia Coppola (Lost in Translation, The Virgin Suicides) looks like biopic of the spoilt Queen of France, with Kirsten Dunst in the title role, and Jason Schwarzman (rather improbably) as Louis XVI. The most unusual thing about this trailer is that, while this looks like a standard period adaptation, complete with fabulous locations and uplift corsetry, the soundtrack to the trailer is New Order's "Age of Consent". Intriguing. Unfortunately, it's not due out until December in the UK.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/trailers/universal/americandreamz/"&gt;American Dreamz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Despite the unpromising title, this is obviously an American satire, with a dumb Southern US president, played by Dennis Quaid, and the host of a reality TV show where new pop stars are discovered, played by Hugh Grant. As this is directed by &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0919369/"&gt;Paul Weitz&lt;/a&gt; (American Pie, In Good Company, About a Boy) it's anyone guess which of these three previous films it might resemble. Due for release in April.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/trailers/focus_features/brick/"&gt;Brick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This looks like a noir thriller, with the novel twist of being set in a high school. Joseph Gordon-Levitt (Third Rock from the Sun) plays the Marlowe-esque character drawn into shady dealings. Looks good, but no UK release date yet according to &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I viewed these from Apple's trailers site: &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/trailers"&gt;apple.com/trailers&lt;/a&gt;, where you'll need Quicktime to view them. &lt;a href="http://www.empiremagazine.co.uk"&gt;Empire Magazine&lt;/a&gt; also has a great site, and will show all the possible trailers in all formats available.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/films" rel="tag"&gt;films&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/reviews" rel="tag"&gt;reviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/02/film-trailers.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114070357751566774'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114070357751566774'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-114063031437386244</id><published>2006-02-22T17:43:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-02-23T14:57:57.700Z</updated><title type='text'>Meme: Top Ten iTunes most played</title><content type='html'>I don't think I've done a &lt;a href="http://thedailymeme.com/what-is-a-meme/"&gt;meme&lt;/a&gt; on here before, but I just saw a good one over at &lt;a href="http://www.scalzi.com/whatever/004036.html"&gt;Whatever&lt;/a&gt; and thought that I would be interested in the results, so maybe you are too.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So here is the top ten tracks in my iTunes library by play count (how many times they have been played on either iTunes or my iPod). Like &lt;a href="http://www.scalzi.com/whatever/"&gt;John Scalzi&lt;/a&gt;, I have included only the most played track from each album to remove the effect of playing the whole album a lot:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;All Star, Smashmouth - Shrek Soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Right Place, Eddi Reader - Eddi Reader&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The 59th Street Bridge Song (Feeling Groovy), Simon &amp;#38; Garfunkel - Greatest Hits&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Big Time Sensuality, Bjork - Debut&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Caramel, Suzanne Vega - Greatest Hits, but I heard it first on the soundtrack to The Truth about Cats and Dogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Layla, Eric Clapton - Unplugged&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Respect, Aretha Franklin - First Lady of Soul&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;One Week, Barenaked Ladies - Stunt&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Weather With You, Crowded House - Woodface&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stan, Eminem - Marshall Mathers LP&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Most of those I identify as upbeat songs that I play to get me in a good mood - especially All Star. They are also all songs that have featured in my CD collection for quite a long while - but I suppose that is inevitable when you count since I started using iTunes (circa 2003). If only you could count the most played tracks this year...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags start --&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:right;font-size:10px;"&gt;Technorati Tags: &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/iTunes" rel="tag"&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/music" rel="tag"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/meme" rel="tag"&gt;meme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- technorati tags end --&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/02/meme-top-ten-itunes-most-played.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114063031437386244'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/114063031437386244'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-113993981944027973</id><published>2006-02-14T17:55:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-02-14T17:56:59.510Z</updated><title type='text'>The discipline of writing</title><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;I have been reading a lot of &lt;a href="http://www.wilwheaton.net"&gt;Wil Wheaton&lt;/a&gt; recently, mostly because he's been writing a lot. He's been making himself write for at least 10 minutes a day, and it seems to be working for him - making him more creative and productive. I find it inspirational(as well as funny and true and good writing), and it has spurred me, once again, into trying to write more regularly on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is a strange truism that if you want something done, give it to someone who's busy. When your day is full, it is easy to accommodate another task or two; when it is empty, you procrastinate, on the basis that you have plenty of time, and will find just the right moment for the task. And of course, you don't. Time drifts along, and suddenly it's 16:49 and you wonder 'Where has my day gone? When I had a job, I would have done 7 hours work by now - I can't possibly have done 7 hours worth of anything today.' And you forget that of those 7 hours, by no means all of them used to be dedicated to real-cranking-through-it work, but this does not diminish the fact that once again, you seem to have wasted your day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/02/discipline-of-writing.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113993981944027973'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113993981944027973'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-113969449041968543</id><published>2006-02-11T21:47:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-02-11T21:48:11.870Z</updated><title type='text'>What Every Woman Wants</title><content type='html'>Browsing through the weekend papers online, I came across &lt;a href="http://news.ft.com/cms/s/e284c6f0-9a24-11da-8b63-0000779e2340.html"&gt;a story in the FT&lt;/a&gt; which featured this tagline:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"Forget the lingerie, what every woman wants is a classic accessory and this year's essential item is the Fendi B bag."&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now, last time I checked, I am a woman, and I have have no idea what a Fendi B bag is, still less do I want one. It made me think, though, about the use of the phrase 'every woman wants'. I am generally opposed to lumping together 51% of the world's population as if we automatically had some secret bond and secret password. But I was curious as to what else 'every woman' was supposed to be after. I little Google New search turned up these gems:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.prweb.com/releases/2006/2/prweb339973.htm"&gt;Every woman wants to feel sexy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.vanguardngr.com/articles/2002/columns/fashionpersonality/fp11022006.html"&gt;Every woman wants to feel special&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://news.independent.co.uk/media/article343556.ece"&gt;Every woman wants to look great&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.prweb.com/releases/2006/2/prweb344447.htm"&gt;Every woman wants to go on vacation and know that they can swim and sun without having to worry about the mascara running&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I particularly like that last one. &lt;br /&gt;It depresses me to think that, while generalisations will always be around, the generalisation for women always seems to tend towards material acquisitions and insecurity. Is this the reality? Let's have a look at a Google News search for 'every man wants'. Well firstly, in contrast to 13 results for women, we get only 4 for men:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.inweekly.net/article.asp?artID=2312"&gt;...every man wants a whole lot of themselves in Carmen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Every man wants to be ...  a complete Don Juan&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/main.jhtml?xml=/sport/2006/01/21/sfntyl21.xml&amp;#38;sSheet=/sport/2006/01/21/ixfooty.html"&gt;Every man wants to date a teenage pin-up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.kobtv.com/index.cfm?viewer=storyviewer&amp;#38;id=23867&amp;#38;cat=NMTOPSTORIES"&gt;Coble told a woman who ran a stop sign that he wanted "what every man wants" in exchange for tearing up the citation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So that's fairly clear - sex, sex, sex and sex. Certainly just as stereotypical, but (in this extremely unscientific sample) fewer results. But maybe the sample is really skewed because of the pool that Google News draws from. Let's have a look at just The Guardian for now:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/focus/story/0,,1535037,00.html"&gt;This season, every woman wants to be a bag lady.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0,,1232609,00.html"&gt;Yet no one likes to mention this for fear of offending feminists who would have us believe that every woman wants to do a job rather than stay at home.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/editor/story/0,,1021893,00.html"&gt;Every woman wants to look good in her Jimmy Choos, but is foot surgery really the way to do it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,,257504,00.html"&gt;Long hair is what every woman wants.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://football.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,,1651652,00.html"&gt;Well, I think it's just the thing that every man wants - to have a son and heir.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://film.guardian.co.uk/features/featurepages/0,,1230789,00.html"&gt;Every man wants to chase a pretty girl if he sees one.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://books.guardian.co.uk/reviews/artsandentertainment/0,,855703,00.html"&gt;Every man wants to be a superman, to make love to anything.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,436145,00.html"&gt;... every man wants to be in his missus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So what have we learned? Maybe not that much. Maybe that women are stereotyped as fashion-obsessed shopaholics, whilst men are stereotyped as sex obsessed - which is perhaps confirmed by looking at the magazines aimed at Men's and Women's issues. Or maybe that those who write (or are quoted as saying) such lazy phrases as 'every man/woman wants' aren't to be relied on for their lightning insights. Whatever. It troubles me.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It also troubles me that all Motorola has to do to get a runaway success phone is &lt;a href="http://blogs.guardian.co.uk/technology/archives/2005/10/19/pink_pound_what_do_women_really_want.html"&gt;make it pink&lt;/a&gt;. And that all a girl wants for Valentine's day is a &lt;a href="http://www.engadget.com/2006/02/08/valentines-day-engadget-style/"&gt;pink laptop&lt;/a&gt;. Ah well. At least we can vote.</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/02/what-every-woman-wants.html'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113969449041968543'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113969449041968543'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-113796581567054663</id><published>2006-01-22T21:35:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-01-22T21:36:55.710Z</updated><title type='text'>Farmers Market</title><content type='html'>I like going to Farmer's Markets but I don't always have the get-up-and-go required to get there. Which is one reason why I like &lt;a href="http://www.lfm.org.uk/mary.asp"&gt;Marylebone Farmer's Market&lt;/a&gt;. It is held on Sunday mornings, when I am much more likely to have the time to potter around, and only starts at 10am, meaning it doesn't finish until 2pm and I have plenty of time to drag myself out of bed and get there.&lt;br /&gt;This morning I went in search of nothing in particular but didn't want to buy a ton of food as I had done a big shop on Friday.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I came away with two nice looking pheasants, a big bag of kale to eat with them, and a loaf of Pugliese bread from Exeter Street Bakery. Then I got some &lt;a href="http://www.nealsyarddairy.co.uk/thecheeses.html#"&gt;Kirkham's Lancashire&lt;/a&gt; and some &lt;a href="http://www.cheese.com/Description.asp?Name=Tomme%20de%20Savoie"&gt;Tomme de Savoie&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.lafromagerie.co.uk"&gt;La Fromagerie&lt;/a&gt;, which has it's Marylebone outpost opposite the car park where the market is held.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I had a vague idea that I might follow &lt;a href="http://lifeandhealth.guardian.co.uk/experts/matthewfort/story/0,,1691209,00.html"&gt;Matthew Fort's excellent ideas&lt;/a&gt; from yesterday's paper and braise the pheasant with chestnuts, but I got home and looked again at the recipe and realised that I was short many of the ingredients. So I turned to Nigel Slater's Kitchen Diaries, where he pot-roasts pheasant with vermouth and celery. In the end I compromised by pot-roasting using Nigel's method, but with Matthew's flavourings of a little Marsala, allspice, juniper berries and bay. I roasted some potatoes in the duck fat leftover from last week, and braised some kale. An excellent meal - all moistened with the unthickened marsala-ey juices from the pot-roast.&lt;br /&gt;And to go from the sublime to the ridiculous, we finished it all off with Jamaica Ginger Cake (bought), Bird's custard and bananas!</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/01/farmers-market.htm'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113796581567054663'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113796581567054663'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6696593.post-113706348239533109</id><published>2006-01-12T10:58:00.000Z</published><updated>2006-01-12T10:58:02.450Z</updated><title type='text'>The Kitchen Diaries</title><content type='html'>&lt;div style="float: right; margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;"&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/48193103@N00/85588314/" title="photo sharing"&gt;&lt;img src="http://static.flickr.com/36/85588314_120360fedc_m.jpg" alt="" style="border: solid 2px #000000;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 0.9em; margin-top: 0px;"&gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/48193103@N00/85588314/"&gt;kitchen_diary&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;  Originally uploaded by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/48193103@N00/"&gt;louise_marston&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;One of the wonderful things I got for Christmas (thank-you Jenny!) was Nigel Slater's new book, The Kitchen Diaries. I am a big fan of Mr Slater's, and have several of his books. I look out for his columns each week in &lt;a href="http://www.observer.co.uk"&gt;the Observer&lt;/a&gt; and I particularly like the way he writes with greed and hunger about the food he cooks.&lt;br /&gt;In case you have not seen this book yet, it is a record of a year of Mr Slater's cooking and eating, arranged chronologically, so you always have a recipe to hand that is appropriate for the season. What could be better for re-adjusting to English seasons than this?&lt;br /&gt;So far I have made two of January's recipes: Dal and Pumpkin Soup and Marmalade Cake - both were wonderful (and both orange - I do have a bias for orange foods: pumpkin, carrot soup, mangoes, orange juice - you get the idea) .&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Partly as a result of this inspiration, and partly as a result of the good advice of my cooking teacher at &lt;a href="http://www.tantemarie.com"&gt;Tante Marie's&lt;/a&gt;, I have bought myself a thick notebook to keep my own cooking diary. In it I am recording where I make a recipe from a book, and when I make something up, as well as changes and adjustments I made as I went along and tasting notes on how it turned out. I let you know how it goes...&lt;br clear="all" /&gt;</content><link rel='alternate' type='text/html' href='http://www.usingmainlyspoons.com/Blog/2006/01/kitchen-diaries.htm'></link><link rel='self' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113706348239533109'></link><link rel='edit' type='application/atom+xml' href='http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6696593/posts/default/113706348239533109'></link><author><name>louise</name></author></entry></feed>